hello Frank de Freitas how are you doing
hello Alec
yes am I calling a good time it's it's
the pre-arranged time and you're right
on the money okay
you're a minute early
[Laughter]
are things going well for you yes okay
this is the first show that I've ever
done where someone has called me
so I I was actually a little confused as
to uh what I needed to do here you know
should I have headphones on when the
phone rings I didn't even know if the
phone would ring
because it all goes into a mixer board
you know that's pretty funny so it seems
like it turned out okay okay that's
great well we have a lot of things to
talk about I thought we would talk a
little bit about the history of integraf
cover a little bit about the company and
also your announcement of your new laser
diode systems that you're going to be
bringing
on soon
but first
since you have the pulse of holography
through your business obviously let me
ask you a couple questions
okay we'll make the answer simple yeah
the answer would either be up or the
answer would be down how's that okay
okay
holography and education
up that's good
professional use of holography
if you define broadly holography well
I'm only up or down right so that would
be I guess overall up up that's good too
you consider holographic label security
is professional but if you're talking
about holographic art I think there's
some potential there
Wales that was a very actually very
encouraging yeah
amateur holography
definitely up on that don't you think
yeah definitely yeah so we've got three
UPS there
that's good
that's right I always want to try and
get a finger on the pulse of holography
and where it's at
unfortunately I haven't seen a hologram
anywhere in ages outside of my own
Studio
you know when you say it's up
but it's still uh probably a slow uh
slope on that mm-hmm
I think education is
particularly
in the in the junior highs and high
schools as they're beginning to do that
and we're finding a lot of summer camps
to bring into it in fact this past
summer we helped a camp set up a lab and
they talked over a thousand students
making Holograms a thousand wow what
camp was this
I see they had there's a there's several
actually there's three of them there's
three summer science camps uh for kids
and each one of them had about 300 400
students uh making whole grams are they
through museums
no they're not actually three
universities
some Foundation money to help set up
camps uh on Optics and things like that
and a lot coming a part of that and
we're helping them set up curricula and
if we give them pretty steep discounts
too so that they can really make it
affordable yeah
well you know
as far as careers go it's it's
holography is in and of itself not too
many people would probably suggest to
someone
to become a professional holographer
when there are so many other choices in
physics and Optics and photonics but
holography is a wonderful segue
two
physics Optics and those types of
careers
that's correct yeah
I think my father Dr Young uh aptly puts
it if the past Century was a century of
electronics and you've seen how that's
completely changed the world the next
century is really going to be the center
of Optics
what else can you learn five Nobel uh
you know prize winning uh ideas than in
holography
and it's fun for kids bottom line that's
very important to keep kids interests
that's right because you're competing
against MTV
competing against iPods
anytime you're in a classroom you know
you may be talking about George
Washington for a week but
it's not going to cut it with some kids
you know about hologography it's
something that they can
bring one of their favorite objects into
class and the workshop and do a hologram
of it and put it under the light and see
it and everyone's very excited about it
right and I think another thing that we
oftentimes bring up particularly is some
teachers will ask you know how can I set
up my curricula what else should I teach
besides how to make the Hologram we have
to bring it into the you know the
the context of today in which you know
you're looking at some of this new
holographic
um Innovations particularly in
holabratic storage if you look at
holographic discs you know looking at
making that 300 gigabyte disks to even
terabyte which is a gigabyte
and what is that base stands based on
holographic you know uh basically
multi-channel Holograms and so there's a
lot of application there and then you
also look of course at smart Holograms
what they're doing with
diabetes treating diabetes or monitoring
diabetes and other diseases there's
actually a lot of applications of
holograms that a lot of people actually
are not as aware of
and it's actually an important field and
you'll see that I think holography will
start
uh
uh you know not only becoming
more used but I think it'll become more
known as well yeah
well hopefully not too many people know
anything about the magnetic hard drives
within their PCS
and not many people know
the laser systems that are in the CD
players and DVD players so it'll
probably be behind the scene and but at
least people know that it's there people
know that they do have a hard drive in
the computer and they do have laser
systems in
players and see
the seed as well yeah
I placed my first order with integraf I
believe in 1982 or 1983 how old were you
that I would have been about 15 then 15.
did you help your dad out back then oh
yeah in fact uh I think you asked about
the little history in a graph but I can
also start about my own little history
sure uh very interesting that I I think
I've been living around holography all
my life uh probably because my you know
my father started in the 1960s initially
I was probably just the object of his
uh with the Lloyd cross uh you know the
uh cilantro hologram my brother my
sister and I were in that that was my
first exposure truly true exposure
television literally and figuratively
but thereafter was helping my father on
some of the workshops uh during the
Summers and then later on actually has
participated I believe in five out of
the seven symposia on International
geography ranging from a
as being the busboy
to uh more recently you know attending
it at a at a higher level
and so uh Instagram has been around uh
for about actually 30 years and yeah 73
right
73 I believe right yeah and uh yeah and
you asked by how it started well
basically uh my father was
trying to help educate education and
help promote holography and it turns out
that as he was making Holograms many his
colleagues would ask him where'd you get
to film
give them a little piece here a little
piece there okay now here's some well
ended up that more and more people kept
asking well where'd you get the film
that ends up
in order to
sing and spending time on it we the
need to go on a kind of
Clinic because just too many inquiries
started coming in we're getting at the
film
at that time uh he was getting some I
believe from agfa direct directly from
agfa that's right uh directly from agfa
and I believe there's a difference
another Supply I believe it was ilford
actually okay yeah Kodak because we had
uh in the past uh been distributed for
Kodak ill for Milford and actually the
DuPont polymer yeah his early work
probably was when Kodak
yep yeah
I know there were there were several
distribute
one not too far from me here which was
Keystone scientific
oh geez what were some of the other
names the names uh just you know slipped
By Me Now
yeah there was a it's a still some of
our Niche industry you probably noticed
it kind of full bloom and so players
that come in and out and uh somehow
endograph has a has survived and uh
today it's
um I think we're probably one of the few
uh Distributors around that kind of do
it on a full-time basis so you'll be
able to you know basically ship the same
day so someone calls that morning yeah
we can ship it up that next day so we've
come to a scale that's large enough to
be able to support that but still I
would say definitely a niche market yeah
absolutely and uh you still have to keep
the prices at a certain level just to be
able to stay in
it's unfortunate that the recording
material still
you know are so expensive when you when
you take into consideration what the
cost of you know all the other equipment
needed to make a hologram you know
you know easily put a fairly decent
experimental holography system together
like a little studio for a hundred
dollars
and then they're going to spend you know
220 for a couple plates
out the front on the sides of the plate
of course but yeah the prices we've
pretty much try to maintain it I don't
think we've actually had a price
increase for something like five years
oh it's not anything that you can do you
know it's not your fault yeah it's a
tough one it's definitely a tough cookie
to crack because we're trying to make it
more affordable in fact so what we're
doing is some of the new products that
we have coming down the road we're
actually working with a manufacturer to
produce some film uh actually we've been
very happy the results will be finding
it as comparable to agfa and actually uh
the Fuji except that it won't be um it's
not uh
chromatic just red sensitive now but I'd
we have a high quality film coming at a
price that's significantly lower than
um what you know customers were used to
at least with the aqua films yeah well
it's fantastic unfortunately be
somewhere near the
the slavish place but but still you know
higher quality for the same price is not
a bad it's always not a bad thing yeah
absolutely yeah
yeah so you've got a lot of interesting
new things coming up it's on your
website I actually want to get a box of
plates from you but I'm I'm leaving next
week and I didn't want to order them
when I was on the website because I
didn't want them arriving you know while
I was gone that's when I noticed your
lasers
your new laser so why don't you tell the
folks that are listening this is big
news I mean that's a wonderful price
it's it's almost science fiction when
you think back 10 20 years you know 50
milliwatt 100 milliwatt diode laser that
you can probably put into your pocket
and why don't you tell the folks what
your plans are and keep in mind that
this will be up you know once this show
goes up it stays up so 10 years from now
you know people will be listening to
this show as well and then you know 10
years from now they'll say 100 milliwatt
Fort too you know for 250 dollars for
one dollar now
we're pretty excited we've got a few
products coming out
coming out uh one is the lasers we also
have a new film I mentioned about it's
called the intergraph xt633 film a new
developer coming out covered
pretty much a d19 mix uh I've been
saying except that it's really to be
used with a new film and then the lasers
oh I'm sorry one more thing with the
lasers we also have the lazy safety
goggles
when you start working
automatic list price 20 lower than
pretty much the any manufacturer we buy
the best laser goggle some
to really encourage the use of them but
the lasers we were coming out with one
is a 50 milliwatt uh let's just put it
this way manufacturer listed or
specified as 50 as you know usually
doesn't come out 50 comes up another
about 30 40. yeah
um but depending on how you you know you
power it up and then they've got 100
milliwatt which comes out really around
80. uh
uh but basically these are two uh down
lasers very similar to the laser that we
have now for 35 which is a four
milliwatt in terms of having a couple of
it's got a coherence length about one
meter
it's got frequency stability
and so that makes it possible to make
Holograms in the first place yes uh and
then third you also have the removable
and adjustable collimating lens which is
really a sweet feature because
you can simply unscrew the lens and have
the lights shut right out therefore you
do not need the laser beam to go through
any specific other lenses yeah
what do you end up with is a beam that's
extremely clear because it doesn't have
to pass through four different surface
lens nor the exterior lens and so if
you're doing a Denny Sue hologram you
can pretty much sign it like a
flashlight make a hologram uh of course
you could put the lens back on and then
do split
uh a technical director my father Dr
Jung actually replaced his uh heany
laser with this one and so we've got two
of them one is a 50 the other 100 100
and 100 is going to be I'll probably
listed around around 245 200
45 cents which is you know like 10 times
more more than 10 times cheaper than a
bit
oh my goodness yes and uh you know
thousands of dollars versus 250
and then the 50 milliwatt were going to
list it about 175.
um
milliwatch within actually a few days to
uh within a week okay
we'll run into a little delay on some of
the specs we found a little fault on it
and we had to have it changed the delay
on the 50 or The 100 on the
okay
uh we're trying to see when we can get
that but hopefully you know we were
originally expecting it like a couple
weeks
I think we're getting a little more
to lift that out a little
bit 100 milliwatts should be ready soon
within a week actually yeah
and then we're going to do just some
final testing just to make sure that
batch is the same
several batches now just to make sure
that you know it's the same it's working
well but so far really great results
um the one caveat I would say about the
laser is that we've only tested up to
exposures about 30 seconds
but remember you know we'll talk about
100 milliwatts so it's not that often
you're going to do exposures longer than
that yeah
but you know we do find with this this
diode lasers with any doubt laser this
whole
there's a temperature uh issue where you
might get a little a shift and so
so we've seen some fringes unusual
fringes or actually things not happen
when you don't
you've got short exposures or contact
copy uh this laser does really really
well
yeah I imagine it's uh
single brass housing so
that's right single brass housing and
this time we actually have the entire uh
even the circuit housed I think in our
on our smaller one still not house okay
ideal but this one we've got a house so
you get a little more robustness in
terms of you know and
Longevity on it and
[Applause]
again the same as before 2D battery and
a battery holder and so it's really
simple
is it possible to run it off of
[Music]
Source you know like one of the wall
warts
yeah you can certainly do that uh you
can still run it off that on some
professors teachers or those who have
access to that metronics cancellation
certainly do that and it's also possible
to run it through a Tec controller so
you do have temperature you know
stability yeah and that should also fix
the problem as well great
exciting stuff yeah really we're pretty
excited about that and then we're also
looking at some uh our current Holocaust
as you know you know so I think the is
low at 99 to make Holograms and
it's pretty it's probably one of the the
most affordable out there today
and then we've got
of course the other two Holo kits you
know using plates but now we're looking
at some what we call middle and higher
end equipment
yeah yeah looking at for the next half
year or so middle and meaning there's a
lot of people are graduating from the
whole kit the whole kit you can make six
to
but usually in a more basic level you
know you can do interferometry yeah
even multi-channel with it and uh but
while finding there's a lot of people
that are graduating from that want to
move at the next level but but four
thousand dollars
and so we're looking at something that's
in between probably nearly a four or
five hundred dollar where you can get
all the equipment
all together to set up your lab and then
finally we're looking at some really
schools and professors and that have you
know Foundation funds and really want
the whole Optical table as well so we
try to put together some packages there
as well
um the idea is really really can make
Holograms and holography a little more
accessible to people at all levels
depending if you're a beginner or if
you're an expert yeah
I don't know if this would be a
population Den
dependent or not but do you find
specific areas of the country that are
more likely to be working with
hologography than others
huh that's a good question
um
I I actually we see a pretty good spread
I think in the past it was probably very
Chicago based New York based in West
Coast
uh but now what we're finding is
actually uh Florida is beginning to do a
lot of holography well it's a
requirement in Florida now beginning
this year
right I don't know if you've spoken to
Bill Pugh oh yeah fantastic job on there
really trying to push the importance of
Optics and holography down there and so
whereas we certainly speak to him on a
frequent basis and then we also find
that
uh
it's kind of the South is beginning to
pick up particularly Texas New Mexico
and things like that but generally
speaking is now fairly even although
there's concentrations of course in New
York and the West
of Chicago did you know there were four
states where you have to register lasers
if they're three being above
uh yeah yeah
I don't know if people actually if folks
actually
doing that but I uh I was on the web the
other night looking different things up
and I believe it's New Jersey
New York Texas and Massachusetts
yep yeah you can't even give a laser to
someone else in New York if it's 3B or
above if you give a laser that's 3B or
above to another person in New York
it's an offense
right and one of the things actually I
forgot to mention about the lasers we're
having is we're gonna we are going to
have a we have a clause there that we on
and I
uh certain individuals right now are the
purpose of uh having these lasers out
it's really for the experienced
holographer who knows what they're doing
has these lasers and we're not really
going to be readily uh providing them
for I guess youngsters or first-timers
especially first
family and kids because yeah you know
you know at that level it will hurt your
eyes if you even look at it just for a
Split Second so you really got to know
what you're doing and so we're going to
be we're trying to set up uh before we
release it a way of really in forming
people hey
do you know what you're doing
and then and go
you really want to take that and uh
we're pretty serious about that on the
old days that would be like someone
purchasing a
125 you know which runs at 50 milliwatts
it was you know the expected 50 put out
more if the tube was new but new but it
took two people lift it you know wanted
each
and now you can just put it in your
pocket that's right yeah for a hundred
and some dollars for the 50 milliwatt
right that's right yeah that's right
well I'm going to get one also
okay so uh hold one from I don't know if
uh what if you're back ordered or not
but hold one for me I'll be away next
week but I'll be coming back the week
after yeah we're actually right now
putting together a email uh a mailing
list uh
and uh fortunately we had a couple
delays so far but uh we'll definitely
you know email everybody who has
requested you know information on the
second they come in so that they know
but they're ready to go and so forth
just take a moment to explain once again
your other products that you're bringing
on the market that's new especially the
developer I
uh I've seen some Holograms actually
reflection hold
developed with d19
and with the potassium dichromate bleach
beautiful Holograms you do get a
wavelength shift down to the green but
that's okay too because the eye is most
sensitive to the green
it does a real nice job you said you
have a developer kit that's coming
together that's similar to d19 well it
is actually uh the developer site is
basically d19 you
sodium sulfide the you know sodium
carbonate and potassium bromide and so
forth relatively safe too yeah that's
right and then we've got the uh then we
had a bleach
which will be the uh copper bromide
potassium sulfate uh citric acid and
some potassium
and
that basically this formula with the
the reason why we developed this formula
is partly because we have the new film
coming out and we found that this
particular
formula works best for that film we have
not really tested this formula yet on
others but
I thought on some of the the Fuji the uh
and some of the slavish material yeah
just to see how it works but basically
it's made for the the new film The XP
633 which we don't have on our website
yet
we're still doing some final testing on
it with some uh holography experts and
things like that yeah and what's the
bleach
processing of that new film
that is the bleach is actually very
you've heard about Kodak
it's very similar to it and it is a
copper bromide potassium sulfate citric
acid potassium bromide I see
right now
a little longer but it's for the ideal
uh sake for schools and individuals we
still recommend you know going with the
jd4 with a pft03 or jd2 with pfco1
because the developing
things yeah
particularly the jd4 I mean you can we
can swing on a hologram in less than two
minutes exposure to developing
and so a lot of schools actually still
prefer that
well is there anything else that you'd
like to add I see we're coming up almost
on 30 minutes believe it or not already
and I like I like you know I would talk
to you for hours but I I like to keep
the file sizes small because believe it
or not there are still people that are
on dial up 56 modems
and you have to take file size into
consideration
so half hour audio file you know with
someone
K uh
dial-up modem you know so anything you
want to say or cover before we close out
I think the
I want to let let people know is you
know of course our our mission in a
graph is really to make
programs known
and of course accessible
so we've got a lot of articles
people might be interested in how to
make Holograms step by
said what we call Affordable meaning we
don't try to really rob the bank we try
to keep it reasonable and you'll see
that there's a lot of discounts
forum for disc
and then finally we do
file report we've helped people go from
basically starting with a holography kit
for 99 to now making full color
Holograms to even some of some
professional believe it or not okay yeah
and so and it's all actually free
technical support leading there
and then the final word
we thank you Frank and this is an
invaluable
station and your website
laser holography too you know the
education through this uh the radio show
and your website is exactly the kind of
things that we really believe in which
is how long is out there
it's not that hard to do uh you know
just a little reading and you can
actually do it within an hour yeah
exactly so thank you Frank well thank
you it's nice to see another generation
that's right getting involved new ones
coming right yeah the the little ones
will be moving up into the uh into the
field soon
I'm one of the old I'm not one of the
old Old-Timers I just have one old
behind my old timer so
I see so many new faces and new names
and uh
it really is a new new error and a new
generation and I I appreciate what
you're doing and I probably wouldn't
have been able to get involved with
hologography if it wasn't for your dad
at his company as well you know I mean
he made it easy at one point
that I needed to get started because I
was one of those people as well one time
a long time ago I've never met your dad
yet wow you know
I have to uh I would have loved to have
gone over to the conference and uh
I don't fly which is my problem you know
on airplanes I don't fly on airplanes
and it's
it's taken away a number of
opportunities for me but one day it'll
be nice to meet everybody in holography
I hope I get a chance to do that
yourself included
that's right that's right definitely and
uh you know if we swing by you know a
Pennsylvania and
we'll definitely try to
Drive in Iowa oh absolutely come by
we'll go out for dinner
yeah doors are always open
um same address same phone number and
everything since uh 1982 83 when I first
started the studio here
all right well Alec thank you very much
for taking the time to come on the show
and I have a link to your website and
email address and just about anything
else anybody would need to get in touch
with you
that sounds terrific all right good luck
with the lasers
and you'll be getting an order from me
as soon as I get back after my trip next
week we'll do Frank all right all right
I'll have this I'll have this up later
tonight
all right take care all right good
talking with you bye
[Applause]
[Music]